Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): Joining me now is a top Democrat, the Democratic Senator from Washington, Patty Murray. She is also the Vice Chair of the Senate Appropriations Committee. Senator Murray, thank you so much for joining me today. Really
Speaker 2: appreciate it.
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): Thank you. Good to talk to you today. Wonderful to have you here. So here we are on day two of the shutdown. There is a vote scheduled
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): again tomorrow for the same funding bill.
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): It doesn't seem like it's going to pass, but do you see any off-ramp
Speaker 4: at this point? Are there any negotiations, Senator Murray, happening behind the scenes that you can tell us about?
Speaker 5: Well, certainly we're all talking to our colleagues about what we
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): need, and we've been very clear. What we have told Republicans for weeks now is that we want
to
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): be part of a bill that they are asking our votes for. They've refused to do that. They have sent a partisan vote.
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): bill to us and said just give us your votes,
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): talk to us later, and we're saying no, our constituents are hurting right now. We have hundreds of thousands of people who are in the mail going to get their insurance bills for
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): next year that are going to double, and they can't afford it. It's a simple solution: extend the tax credits.
And
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): all we're asking for is to have a discussion with us, come to us, let's have a negotiation, and to this point.
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): They've not done
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): this. Republicans are in charge in the White House, in the Senate, and in the House for this bill. They need our votes. And we are saying we want to make sure our constituents are taken care of and our
Speaker 9: voices are heard.
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): JUDY WOODRUFF: Senator, Republicans say they are willing to negotiate. They say they just don't want to negotiate over this.
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): funding bill they say let's open up the government then let's have a negotiation why not take that
Speaker 10: tack and allow the government to reopen
Speaker 11: well the irony of that is we have had a government's been open we have been
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): saying for weeks come and talk to us let's figure out how to solve this problem for the people in all of our states and they haven't done it so why would i believe them where is the trust that oh just open government we'll talk to you then
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): they didn't before why would they now give us an assurance that that is what you're going to do that's what we're
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): asking for i wonder how you see these threats by the president to lay off
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): thousands of federal workers clearly trying to turn up the heat to get you all to agree to this funding bill are you feeling pressure given that
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): thousands of federal workers could at the very least receive notification that
Speaker 12: their jobs are going to be eliminated. Well,
Speaker 13 (higher-pitched voice): I will say it is horrendous for this president to threaten
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): people and to cause disruption and to create chaotic situations. Am I surprised? No, that's what he's been doing for months now. What we're saying, he's trying to hurt
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): people. We're trying to help people by getting these ACA tax credits and government funded with assurance to our constituents that they will get their needs met.
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): So he's trying to hurt people, we're trying to
Speaker 3 (higher-pitched voice): hurt people, to help people. I know the people are on our side. As you know, there have been some Democrats who voted
Speaker 4: for the Republican bill earlier this week, one of them, Nevada Senator Catherine Cortez Masto, who said this, quote, "We need a bipartisan solution to address this impending health care crisis, but we should not be swapping
Speaker 14: the pain of one group of Americans for another."
How
Speaker 14: do you respond to her? And I know,
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): Catherine, very well. We talked. We talked again today. Both of us want to find a solution out of this. No
one
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): wants to hurt anybody. The president and the Republicans right now are willing to hurt people by having this shutdown that they are creating. And we are saying we want to help people. Just come and talk with us and negotiate.
Speaker 6 (higher-pitched voice): and hear our voices so we can move forward.
I
Speaker 15: think that's what a democracy is about. I think that this is what this moment is about. I think that's what this country wants, and we are willing to stand up tall and fight for it.
Speaker 4: - Senator, how long are you willing to have this fight? Because right now it doesn't seem as though there's any resolution, any end in sight. Are you willing to wait
Speaker 13 (higher-pitched voice): months if it takes that long?
Speaker 13 (higher-pitched voice): Well, I am really hopeful that our Republican colleagues who are feeling
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): the heat on this will continue to do what they have been doing over the last several days and talking with us about how we move forward. But what it's really going to take is President Trump and the leader of the Senate, Thune, and the leader of the House, Johnson, to come to us and work this out. And I really hope that they will do that soon and not continue to treat us like we don't exist. Are you
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): confident that your caucus will stay unified, Senator?
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): I
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): am confident that we know who we're fighting for. We're fighting for the people in our state who deserve a say in
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): how their government is funded, how they spend their tax dollars, and how they make sure that they get their health care covered. I am very confident we're standing where we
Speaker 10: are. And just finally, I mean, as you look at this situation, you look at the polls, early polls
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): show more.
Speaker 1 (higher-pitched voice): People right now are pointing the finger at Republicans, but about a quarter of a people say they don't know who to blame. So that could easily shift over time. Senator, are you worried about the political pain it could cause to Democrats in the long run, particularly ahead of the midterms?
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): Well, I think.
THE
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): PEOPLE IN OUR COUNTRY HAVE BEEN WATCHING THIS WHITE
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): HOUSE AND THIS PRESIDENT FOR MONTHS NOW. USE CHAOS. HE HAS FIRED PEOPLE. HE HAS WITHHELLED FUNDS. PEOPLE THAT ARE EXPECTING GRANTS TO HELP POLICE IN THEIR COMMUNITIES, TO PROJECTS THAT HAVE BEEN PROMISED AND THEY'RE HOLDING UP THE THINGS, THEY'RE THREATENING EMPLOYEES ABOUT FIRING THEM, ALL THIS STUFF. I THINK THEY'RE TIRED OF IT, TOO.
Speaker 8 (higher-pitched voice): And they want to say, hey, sit down, talk with everybody, and move us forward. And
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): that's what we are trying to do, to help people, not hurt them. The White House needs to stop hurting people if they want this country to be strong again.
All
Speaker 17: right, Senator Murray, we will continue to track every twist and turn. We really appreciate your coming on today and bringing us your perspective. Thank you so much.
Speaker 18: Thank you.